בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. פורים שמח. Purim Sameach. Today's דף daf is
דף daf מ"ט. Mem Tet. We pick up at the first line
of, second of, first line, last line on מ"ח עמוד ב'. Mem
Chet amud bet. We've just went through a very fascinating סוגיא sugya
of רב הונא Rav Huna of תליוהו וזבין זביניה זביני, talyuhu vezavin
zvineih zvini, is that if somebody is forced to do a sale
it is good, and we said only when obviously when money changes
hands and somehow that the person in the end of the day
commits to that. I mention an interesting debate, רמב"ם Rambam and ראב"ד
Ra'avad whether you need to say רוצה אני rotzeh ani like you
do by cases of like גט get and a קרבן. korban. And
now the גמרא Gemara continues. איני, Eini, is that really true that
the last thing that we left off with was a case of
two שטרות shtarot that had been signed. One was a שטר מכר
shtar mecher and the other was a שטר מודעא. shtar moda'ah. A
מודעא moda'ah is a testimony of the person selling that he's being
compelled and coerced and that if that is signed prior to the
שטר shtar of the sale, it negates the שטר shtar of the
sale. Okay, and that's what the גמרא Gemara had said. So even
had he been coerced, had there not been the מודעא, moda'ah, it
would have been good because that's the principle of תליוהו וזבין זביניה
זביני. talyuhu vezavin zvineih zvini. But because of the מודעא, moda'ah, that
annulled it. That said that no, even at the end of the
day even with the receiving the money, he still is not doing
it willingly. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, איני
Eini is that really true
that this שטר מודעא shtar moda'ah cancels out the שטר מכר. shtar
mecher. And the key here being that it was the same עדים
edim on both שטרות. shtarot. דאמר רב נחמן, De'amar Rav Nachman, doesn't
רב נחמן Rav Nachman say, עדים שאמרו אמנה היו דברינו אין נאמנים,
edim she-amru amana hayu devareinu ein ne'emanim, if witnesses say, yes, this
is our signature, okay, but it was a שטר shtar of אמנה.
amana. It was a trusted שטר. shtar. What does it mean a
trusted שטר? shtar? It means that
טוביה Tuvia said to מיכאל, Michael, מיכאל, Michael, I'd like to borrow
$100 from you, and I trust you מיכאל Michael so much that
I will have the witnesses sign a שטר shtar right now that
I borrowed $100 from you and give you that שטר shtar and
I trust that eventually you will lend me that money. Okay, so
they did it even though they had not seen it, even though
I had not admitted that I owed the money to him, thank
you very much
because that is a שטר shtar that...
Why would he do that? Because then he has a lien and
the lien is...
So right. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says the better of the bed
and that has something to do with like a principle like עדי
חתימה זכיין לו edei chatima zachyan lo or whatever, that if I
eventually borrow the money from you because the שטר shtar was written
legitimately, could be that actually the liens will kick in retroactively. Okay,
so that's an interesting whole discussion about like to what degree the
signature can make it valid retroactively.
So the witnessing something that didn't happen.
So right, so they're signing something that didn't happen, right, a contract...
Well, so you're obligating yourself. Yes, you are, but the point is
is that if the money never was lent, then the שטר shtar
is never valid. Okay, so they're basically saying yes it's our signatures,
but there's no evidence that the שטר shtar is valid. Okay, or
אין נאמנים, ein ne'emanim, they're not believed. Now certainly if there was
testimony from others that these are their signatures, so then the שטר's
shtar already considered מקוים mekuyam validated. So then they're not just believed
to come and say something that like negates the שטר. shtar. But
even if they are the ones to validate the שטר shtar and
you could say it's a principle like called הפה שאסר הוא הפה
שהתיר, ha-peh she-asar hu ha-peh she-hitir, that the same virtue that we
believe them that it's their signatures, we're going to believe them the
context of the signing of it and that it's not a שטר
shtar that we should necessarily assume its validity because it depends if
the money was lent. Nevertheless, we don't say that. Why don't we
say that? Because before like
when you say הפה שאסר הוא הפה שהתיר, ha-peh she-asar hu ha-peh
she-hitir, it seems like one way of explaining this is the way
it works is it works in two stages. Okay, you said both
things. So first we'll believe what point A that you said, and
then by the same principle that we believe point A we'll believe
point B. So great, we believe point A, we believe it was
your signatures. Now you know what that turns into? That turns this
שטר shtar into a legitimate שטר. shtar. A legitimate שטר shtar has
the status
of שטר כמי שנחקרה עדותן בבית דין דמי, shtar k'mi she-nichra eidutan
b'veit din dami, that it's like we have in front of us
testimony that's already been accepted by court. So let's say you have
witnesses, their testimony was accepted by court, and then they come back
and they say, oh by the way we really didn't mean it,
by the way it really you know even though we said it
it meant in this type of a context and it really wasn't
good and so on. So that's a principle of
כיון שהגיד שוב אינו חוזר ומגיד. kevan she-higid shuv eino chozer u-magid.
Once they've testified they cannot go back and retract their testimony. Now
partly you might want to know is this really retracting, it's contextualizing
their testimony. Okay, but the point is is that that's what's at
stake here. So although they say this all in one sentence, as
soon as they said the first part, you know, that validates the
שטר, shtar, and then that means we're dealing with a שטר shtar
that we know. already have validated and accepted testimony in בית דין
Beis Din *Beis Din*. So now when they're trying to say something
else that would negate the validity of that testimony, it doesn't have
the power to negate. הפה שאסר הוא הפה שהתיר *Hapeh she'asar hu
hapeh she'hitir*, we do believe your next statement, but it doesn't have
the power to negate because you have a statement of two people
that were prepared generally to believe, but even though we're prepared generally
to believe it, it can't negate an accepted testimony that's already been
signed and sealed in court.
So would the other way around work? What? If it's a שטר
shtar *shtar*...
You know what it's like? I'll give you an example if it's
hard for you to understand. שטר shtar... אמנה היו דברינו *Shtar amana
hayu devareinu*. Yeah, but you can't say one without the other. I'll
give you an example of what it's like. When you try to
appeal a case in front of a court, right, you can't, even
if you bring like, even if you get the witnesses to recant
and you bring all this other evidence that the person is innocent,
unless you can actually prove a procedural problem, right, then in theory,
you know, you really can't,
it's not a basis for appeal. Okay. So it's very good, I
totally believe all the evidence points that way, all the witnesses recanted,
okay, but there was nothing procedurally wrong, כמי שנחקרה עדותן בבית דין
דמי *kemi shenechkerah edutan beveit din dami*, you can't review it. So
it's not like we don't believe you, it's like we don't believe
you enough that it can negate what's already been accepted.
So even you believe them that it was an אמנה *amana*?
So
yes, and then it would be a case of almost like, then
it's an interest... yes, because then it's more like you're not the
same witnesses retracting and then you have to deal with like עדים
זוממים או מכחישים *edim zomemim o machishim* type of thing. You mean
if you have
different עדים *edim*?
Yes, then that could work, then that could work. But this is
because they're the same עדים *edim*.
And the גזירת הכתוב *gezeiras
hakesuv* says you can't retract. Exactly, the גזירת הכתוב *gezeiras hakesuv* says
you can't retract this paper. Okay. Fine. מודעא היו דברינו *Moda'ah hayu
devareinu*, similarly, if they say that it was a מודעא *moda'ah*, yes
we signed it, but we had signed... but we had signed an
earlier document or the guy had testified before us earlier that he's
being coerced, then similarly, although it doesn't really contradict, but because it
doesn't... אמנה *amana* contradict? But it has the effect of neutralizing, that's
considered חוזר ומגיד *chozer umaggid*. אין נאמנים *ein ne'emanim*, they're not believed.
So anyway, so how come here it works, the שטר Shtar, מודעא
*shtar moda'ah*? It says no, הני מילי על פה *hani mili al
peh*. No, yes, but here, exactly, הני מילי על פה *hani mili
al peh*, that's when they're coming verbally to testify now that it's
a מודעא *moda'ah* and go against a signed and sealed שטר *shtar*
that it's valid. עד דלא אתי פה אמר לשטרא *ad d'lo asi
peh amar l'shtara*, that verbal testimony can't go against a שטר *shtar*
once they've acknowledged that it's their signatures, that שטר *shtar* is already
signed and sealed testimony. אבל בשטרא אתי שטר אמר לשטר *Aval bishtara
asi shtar amar l'shtar*, one שטר *shtar* can work against another. And
the basic reason here is because, you know, also what's important about
this is not just that the other thing was a שטר *shtar*,
but it was a prior שטר *shtar*. The שטר *shtar* of the
מודעא *moda'ah* preceded that you can't go ahead and sell something and
after I sold something, you know,
to David there I have a regret and I say, oh, you
know what I'll do? I'll go tell witnesses that I was coerced
and get them to sign it, right, a מודעא *moda'ah* after the
sale obviously won't work. It'll just be a way for me to
retract after I've regretted, right, after I've had remorse. So what I'm
going to do is I'm going to... but a מודעא *moda'ah* before
will work. So that's another reason this is better. It's not just
פה *peh* versus שטר *shtar*. It's also a prior שטר מודעא *shtar
moda'ah*, I don't know, works against this, I know. Okay. But because...
yeah, it's a good question. Anyway, fine. But they're both true. Okay.
So it's both that it's signed and sealed testimony of the מודעא
*moda'ah*, it's not just testimony being provided now, and it was actually
occurred prior to the fact. As a matter of fact, מודעא *moda'ah*
has specific language.
I mean, a שטר מכר *shtar mecher* is that I'm selling it
for such and such. Right. A מודעא *moda'ah* is I hereby... isn't
like, don't we have a whole? Yeah, yes. So right, so okay,
so meaning that this was in the way a שטר *shtar* is,
so you don't need to say the שטר מודעא *shtar moda'ah* because
it would have been patently obvious from the way it was written.
No, no, no. But you have a שטר מכר *shtar mecher*. Yeah.
And now they're saying the שטר מכר *shtar mecher* is no good
because the guy gave a מודעא *moda'ah* to us. That doesn't work
if they say that על פה *al peh*. Because now their testimony
is coming later. But if they produce a שטר מכר *shtar mecher*
and they produce a שטר מודעא *shtar moda'ah* that was earlier, then
that שטר מודעא *shtar moda'ah* negates the שטר מכר *shtar mecher*.
Even if they produce a שטר מודעא *shtar moda'ah* after?
Yeah, it doesn't matter when they produce the שטר מודעא *shtar moda'ah*.
It's dated earlier.
But you can always backdate something, can't you?
Yeah, you could lie, but you know, okay, but you're not supposed
to sign it.
In that case, there's a מיגו *migo* here that's not being considered.
You don't have a מיגו *migo*, right, that's true, but you don't
use מיגו *migo* the same way you have עדים *edim*. You don't
need a מיגו *migo*. מיגו *migo* doesn't work like, you know, against
already signed and sealed testimony. עדים *edim* don't work, they're themselves testifying.
So if they say it was a מודעא *moda'ah* that was given
prior, it doesn't work, but if they produce a שטר מודעא *shtar
moda'ah* that was מקובל *mekubal*, like that is now עדות *eidus* that
was accepted prior, then it does work. Right.
Even though they're the same עדים *edim* on both?
Exactly, that's exactly the point. Okay, so גופא אמר רב נחמן אמנה
היו דברינו אין נאמנים מודעא היו דברינו אין נאמנים *Gufa, amar Rav
Nachman: amana hayu devareinu ein ne'emanim, moda'ah hayu devareinu ein ne'emanim*. So
now we just said that. ומר בר רב אשי אמר אמנה היו
דברינו אין נאמנים *U'mar bar Rav Ashi amar: amana hayu devareinu ein
ne'emanim*. That's true, they're not believed, because that's essentially saying that the
testimony was not your testimony, that you testified to something which hadn't
really happened. Even by אמנה *amana*. Exactly, that's exactly the point. Okay,
so גופא *gufa*, אמר רב נחמן *amar Rav Nachman*, אמנה היו דברינו
אין נאמנים *amana hayu devareinu ein ne'emanim*, מודעא היו דברינו אין נאמנים
*moda'a hayu devareinu ein ne'emanim*. So now we just said that. ומר
בר אשי אמר *Umar bar Ashi amar*, אמנה היו דברינו אין נאמנים
*amana hayu devareinu ein ne'emanim*. That's to the נאמנים *ne'emanim* because that's
essentially saying that the testimony was not your testimony, that you testified
to something which hadn't really happened. That's, so now to say that,
you're negating what you said before. מודעא היו דברינו נאמנים *moda'a hayu
devareinu ne'emanim*. Now if they say it was a מודעא *moda'a*, then
they are believed. Now why? That also has the effect of negating
it. You're saying we signed it but we were told it wasn't
a genuine sale. So he says, מאי טעמא *mai ta'ama*, שזה ניתן
לכתוב וזה לא ניתן לכתוב *shezeh nitan likhtov vezeh lo nitan likhtov*.
One of them should have been written and one of them shouldn't
have been written. A שטר אמנה *shtar amana* you're not really supposed
to write, okay, because and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* actually says that
it says that you're not supposed to hold onto a שטר אמנה
*shtar amana*, it says לא ישכון באהליך עולה *lo yishkon be'oholekha avla*.
Like the whole thing is a perversion. You have this thing that
says something happened and it didn't. And it's also very tempting for
you to use, for you to just claim that it happened if
it didn't, even though it didn't, or maybe you'll forget and you'll
think that it happened, right? So it's obviously a very sort of
so therefore the whole thing should never have been written in the
first place, okay. But a שטר מכר *shtar mekher* when somebody's being
coerced, he should write it if you've written him a שטר מודעא
*shtar moda'a*, or he's issued a מודעא *moda'a*. Why should you write
it? Because you want to help this guy get out of his
state of being coerced, okay. So in that case, since it was
acceptable for them to write the שטר *shtar*, they're not saying they
did anything wrong, right? If they said they signed a שטר אמנה
*shtar amana*, it's basically almost like saying משים עצמו רשע *mesim atzmo
rasha*. You shouldn't have signed such a שטר *shtar*, okay. So therefore
it's not going then we don't accept that testimony that you did
something wrong. But if you say you signed a שטר מכר *shtar
mekher* having known that he issued a מודעא *moda'a*, that was appropriate
for you to do. You're helping the guy out, and therefore we
accept your testimony because it's really contextualizing what was said and not
contradicting what was said. Yes?
I'm trying to understand one thing. Let's say they said, okay, this
is my signature, וכולהו *vekulhu*, and then they come back and say
I was a קטן *katan* when I signed it. Would they be
believed?
So that's an excellent question. That's in כתובות Kesubos, *Kesubos*, and that's
I think the answer there is no as well, that it's a
similar type of an issue that if you have a, certainly if
it's כתב ידן יוצא ממקום אחר *ktav yadan yotze mimmakom acher*. If
they say that it was a קטן *katan* when he signed it
and it was not כתב ידן יוצא ממקום אחר *ktav yadan yotze
mimmakom acher*, but then it's basically also then never testifying that it
was legitimate testimony to begin with, so it might be different,
okay. I'd have to double-check. It's a discussion in סוגיא sugya, *sugya*
in כתובות *Kesubos*. Okay. How consistent we are across the board? I
understand. Okay. והבעל אין לו חזקה chazaka. בנכסי אשתו *Vehabba'al ein lo
chazaka benikhsei ishto*. Now we finally move on to a next section
of the משנה Mishnah *Mishna*. A man does not have חזקה chazaka.
*chazaka* in his wife's property. Okay. Now his wife's property, to remind
you, is his wife brings two types of property into the marriage.
One is the נכסי צאן ברזל nichsei tzon barzel. *nikhsei tzon barzel*.
That's property that the actual title transfers to the husband. He completely
owns it. And that's like what one might call the dowry. You
assess what its value is, let's say it's worth ten thousand dollars,
you write in the כתובה kesubah *Ketubah*, the wife brought ten thousand
dollars of dowry into the marriage. And then if the husband dies
before her or divorces her, she has a ten thousand dollar debt
against the estate. Okay. She wouldn't necessarily get the same property back,
it depends whether the value went up or down or whatever, but
she is owed that money of the value of the dowry. That's
called נכסי nichsei... צאן ברזל *nikhsei tzon barzel*.
The value of the dowry that was brought in
at the time it was brought in, indexed for inflation. Exactly.
And is that called נדוניא nedunya. *nedunya*?
That's נכסי צאן ברזל *nikhsei tzon barzel*, yeah. The נדוניא nedunya. *nedunya*,
yes. That is the נדוניא *nedunya*, okay. ודא נדוניא דהנעלת ליה מבי
אבוה *veda nedunya dehan'alat leh mibei avuha*, right? So that is the
נכסי צאן ברזל *nikhsei tzon barzel*, and then it says הכל קיבל
עליו החתן *hakol kibel alav hachatan*
at the value of מאה זקוקים כסף צרוף *me'ah zequqim kesef tzaruf*,
which means we are assessing the value of the נדוניא *nedunya* for
מאה זקוקים *me'ah zequqim*. By the way, a זקוק *zequq* is a
lot more than a זוז *zuz*. מאה זקוקים *me'ah zequqim* of כסף
*kesef*, of silver, and that means that if he dies before her
or divorces her, she gets to take that value out of the
estate. That's the נכסי צאן ברזל *nikhsei tzon barzel* which he completely
takes title of. נכסי מלוג nichsei melog. *nikhsei milog* are things that
she retains title of, but what he has is he has I
think what's called usufruct, which means the, you like that fancy word?
I love usufruct. פירות peirot, *peirot*. He has the right to get
all of the profit and the benefit from them during the marriage.
He has קנין kinyan. פירות peirot *kinyan peirot*, but she retains title.
And that's not written in the כתובה kesubah *Ketubah*. You know why
it's not written in the כתובה kesubah. *Ketubah*? Because no ownership hasn't
changed. She retains title. So it doesn't matter. We don't have to
say it's assessed at this value. It's all still her property. He
just gets the אכילת פירות achilat peirot *akhilat peirot*. Okay. So that's
נכסי מלוג nichsei milug, *nikhsei milog*. So now when we say the
husband doesn't have
חזקה chazaka? *chazaka* in נכסי אשתו *nikhsei ishto*, well, the נכסי צאן
ברזל *nikhsei tzon barzel* he already owns. That's not נכסי אשתו *nikhsei
ishto*. So the נכסי מלוג nichsei milug. *nikhsei milog*, which is נכסי
אשתו *nikhsei ishto*, what she owns, he doesn't get חזקה chazaka. *chazaka*
by working the land and benefiting from the produce because he has
the right to do that. He's sort of like an אריס *aris*
that gets a hundred percent, okay? He has the right to do
that, so of course he's not going to get a חזקה chazakah,
*chazaka*. He gets the produce. So that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, פשיטא *pishita*, isn't this obvious? כיון דאית ליה פירות peirot, *keivan
de'it leh peirot*, since he's entitled to the fruit, פירות peirot. הוא
דקאכיל *peirot hu deka'akhil*. He's eating his fruit.
לא צריכא, דכתב לה, de-chasav lah, you need it for the following
case, that he wrote to her, דין ודברים אין לי בנכסייך. din
u-devarim ein li bi-nechasayich. I am now renouncing any claim I have
against your property. Now, by the way, he really has to say
more than just בנכסייך, bi-nechasayich, he has to say and in the
פירות, peirot. and in the פירות peirot of the פירות, peirot. and
so on, because if he just says he's renouncing claim of the
property, means he has no claim against the title, but he's also
going to also renounce claim to the פירות. peirot, So before the
marriage, he basically says, "I am waiving my right to אכילת פירות
achilat peirot. from your נכסי מלוג. nichsei milug. I am not going
to get the אכילת פירות." achilat peirot. And therefore, now we see
during the marriage that he's eating the פירות. peirot, So since he
waived the right, he's not eating it because he has a right
to do it, so maybe he's eating it because he bought the
property. And if he does it for three years, maybe he has
a חזקה. chazakah, And the okay, so that's the point, because it's
ironic, maybe we should say he bought the property. So that's what
it says, no, קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that still at
the end of the day, since he's the husband, even if he
doesn't have rights, even if he's waived those rights, we could say
the wife is going to let him eat the פירות peirot anyway,
even if he's not legally entitled to it. Okay, so therefore it
could be a case where he legally has waived the rights and
nevertheless there's no חזקה. chazakah Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, וכי כתב לה מאי הוי?
ve-chi chasav lah mai havei?
Now the גמרא Gemara just gets into the technical question. Does writing
this actually mean that he has forfeited his rights? Does it really
work? והתניא, ve-hatanya, didn't we teach in a ברייתא? braita? האומר לחברו
ha-omer le-chavero דין ודברים אין לי על שדה זו, din u-devarim ein
li al sadeh zo, I have no claim against this field, ואין
לי עסק בה, ve-ein li esek bah, and I have no nothing
to do with it, ידי מסולקת הימנה, yadi mesuleket heimena, my hands
are removed from it, לא אמר כלום, lo amar klum, you haven't
said anything because we've seen this before that if you really want
to give up rights you can't just say I am removing my
rights. Once you have those rights you have to actually grant them
back to the person, you need to do a קנין. kinyan So
the גמרא Gemara says, now there's an obvious answer because this actually
if you own something you have to give it back. Here, or
you have to give it. Here, he doesn't own it, he only
has rights, and actually there would be a perfect time, maybe once
he has the rights he would have to do a קנין kinyan.
to give them up, but there would be a perfect time to
waive the rights, which would be when? Before he actually took possession
of them. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמרי דבי ינאי, amri devei
Yannai, the school of רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai says, no, בכותב לה
ועודה
ארוסה. be-chotev lah ve-odah arusah.
No, it's a case where he wrote before the נישואין. nisu'in. There
was קידושין, kiddushin, so he was already enough in the context that
it was meaningful to waive the right, but he only got those
rights at נישואין. nisu'in. And before the נישואין, nisu'in, he said "I
am hereby waiving my right", and therefore at the time of the
נישואין, nisu'in, once he's already said that, he doesn't, you don't force
that upon him against his will, וכדרב כהנא, u-che-Rav Kahana, like רב
כהנא Rav Kahana says when they get married.
When they get
married, he doesn't have the right to פירות.
peirot And if he didn't do that before he got married and
he wrote it after he got married, at נישואין nisu'in he would
have the right to פירות, peirot, so renouncing it then wouldn't
accomplish anything, in which case we see he can't claim a חזקה?
Chazakah, No, he can't. He can't either way, but it's just obvious
in the case.
Protecting the woman.
Whether he has or hasn't waived the right, yes, we'll get to
the protecting the woman in a minute. Whether he has or hasn't
waived the right, he doesn't have a חזקה. Chazakah It's just he,
if he hasn't waived the rights, it's obvious. If he has waived
the right, it's a bigger חידוש. chiddush. So we want to make
a case where it's a חידוש. chiddush. So the חידוש chiddush is,
let me just finish, that if he has waived the rights, what's
the context where he waived the rights? That he did it before
the נישואין, nisu'in, and therefore it's valid, וכדרב כהנא, u-che-Rav Kahana, דאמר
רב כהנא, de-amar Rav Kahana, because רב כהנא Rav Kahana says, נחלה
הבאה לו לאדם ממקום אחר אדם מתנה עליה שלא יירשנה. nachalah ha-ba'ah
lo le-adam mi-makom acher adam matneh aleha she-lo yirashenah.
If somebody gets is going to get an inheritance from somewhere else,
a person can stipulate before you get it that you do not
want to receive it, and that's valid. Now, this phrase is very
misleading, because when you say נחלה, nachalah, the first thing that you
think about is real inheritance. So can a person really say, you
know, their father is on the deathbed, and they're actually going to
say before the father dies, "I waive my rights as an heir.
I'm not going to inherit." And the answer is no, that we
actually say that ירושה yerushah happens against your will. That's just the
דין תורה. din Torah. It ought to happen automatically, you cannot waive
it. So this idea really applies to benefits that you get from
somewhere else that are, and actually the way the גמרא Gemara articulates
it, that basically are like of a rabbinic nature. If the rabbis
award you some benefits, for example, like a, you know, the husband
has certain rights with, you know, with his wife, a father with
his daughter, you know, there's other types of cases in which somebody,
the rabbis gave certain rights. So if you waive that before you're
about to receive it, then actually it's legitimate.
Does it mean your will, or we're not directly related?
You mean let's say it's a case of like מתנת שכיב מרע
matnat shechiv mera is an interesting example because that actually is something
that is rabbinic. Basically this is limited to rabbinic types of things.
So I guess yeah, מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shechiv mera maybe that
would work.
Or a bequest to somebody else. Like you know you just put
it in.
Putting someone in a will is a מתנת שכיב מרע. matnat shechiv
mera. If it's a מתנת בריא matnas bari to be חל chal
אחר מיתה achar misa then that's a standard then that's a real
קנין. kinyan Generally this is applied to דרבננ'ס d'rabanans not to דאורייתא'ס.
d'oraitsas.
Whoever it is
you know your
rich uncle puts them in their will.
But the way wills work is basically like a type of a
מתנת שכיב מרע. matnas shchiv mera. We're going to get that's the
end of בבא בתרא. Bava Basra. A will doesn't really how does
a will work? You have to give a gift while you're alive,
right? So the only way either you have it it will either
work by having it take effect the second before I die, then
it's a real קנין kinyan and then maybe it wouldn't work because
we'd say you can't renounce that. But if it's working on the
principle of מתנת שכיב מרע matnas shchiv mera then that's a דרבנן.
d'rabanan. So the general principle is is that this works for דרבננ'ס.
d'rabanans. Okay.
If you take a look the first line of the רשב"ם: Rashbam:
נחלה הבאה לו העתידה לבוא לו תהא כנחלה דרבנן. nachala haba lo,
ha'atida lavo lo, t'hei k'nachala d'rabanan. Okay. כדפריש לקמן אדם יכול להתנות
עליה kedifareish lekaman adam yakhol lehatnos aleha etc. So you have to
take a look about you know about the application. תוספות Tosafos also
discusses it but we basically apply this to like דרבננ'ס. d'rabanans. So
this is a דרבנן. d'rabanan. Yeah Rabbi Dov you had a question?
I just wanted to ask the point of שכיב מרע, shchiv mera,
in other words it's a real קנין kinyan and then miraculously he
gets up out of bed and he's healed. And then it goes
back in.
Right, but what makes it really דרבנן d'rabanan that could be worked
that could work in general that could just be because your דעת
da'as was on the assumption that you the guy was gonna die
etc. But what makes it a דרבנן d'rabanan קנין is that it
takes place not before death but after death or at death.
Yes.
In the case can the person bestowing the inheritance
renounce the person he wants to give it to before he dies?
Yeah, well also
biblically like a gift oh you
mean you mean a biblical inheritance? No you cannot renounce. Either way?
Right, but we'll see cases that whatever. That's all the end of
בבא בתרא Bava Basra all those cases of inheritance.
One quick question yes? But doesn't this mean but also nothing to
do with מקום אחר makom acher mean like later? Like in other
words I know this guy owes me money I don't have it
yet it's not like
oh you could be מוחל mochel a debt. Yeah you could be
מוחל mochel a debt
but that's a little different. That's not some that's not some award
something you're going to be awarded. Okay. All right so שלא ירשנה.
shelo yirshena. וכדרבא ukid'rava
now this is like רבא Rava דאמר רבא כל האומר אי אפשי
בתקנת חכמים כגון זו שומעין לו. d'amar Rava kol ha'omer iy efshi
betakanas chachamim kigone zo, shomin lo. Anybody who says I don't want
like the what the rabbis have given me we would listen to
that person. Now this is actually interesting because the application is what's
כגון זו? kigone zo? So this is actually very interesting and very
relevant because this is the case about a woman who says one
of the תנאי כתובה, t'nai kesubah, one of the sort of
ongoing sort of obligations of the כתובה ketubah is that the husband
gets the wife's earnings מעשה ידיה כנגד מזונות. ma'aseh yadeha keneged mezonos.
He provides for her. All right now that was done. The key
question is for whom was that done to protect whose interests? So
if we say it's to protect the husband's interests, we want to
make sure that he gets his earnings but once we're giving him
his earnings it's only fair that he provide for her, then she
cannot say I want I don't want this. But if we say
it's to protect her interests, we want to make sure she's provided
once we make sure that she's provided for he's going to get
something in exchange he'll get her earnings then she because she's considered
the beneficiary of it then she's in a position to say you
know what I don't need this. I actually earn a very nice
salary and he's actually not able to provide for me equal to
my salary I would much rather keep my salary and have him
keep his you know keep his paying for the food bills. Okay
so because the whole thing in principle was done to protect her
interests, which it was, that's a whole debate in כתובות, but we
wind up saying that the you know the עיקר ikkar is the
מזונות. mezonos. Meaning our prime concern was is the מזונות עיקר mezonos
ikkar or the מעשה ידיה עיקר? ma'aseh yadeha ikkar? So we say
the מזונות mezonos are עיקר. ikkar. The primary concern was to make
sure that she was provided for. And therefore once that was taken
care of we give him the earnings in exchange. So if she
doesn't need that and since she's the beneficiary she's able to say
אי אפשי בתקנת חכמים. iy efshi betakanas chachamim. I don't want this,
I'm going to keep my earnings to myself thank you very much,
and she's entitled to and she keeps the earning and the husband
doesn't have to provide for her. Now that is very relevant להלכה
l'halacha because
for example you know when in the states when we talk about
a prenuptial agreement, we talk about it in terms of a way
of using it to get a גט get to be given. But
in Israel they've got an additional issue which is is that if
a case goes to a בית דין and not a בית משפט
Beis Mishpat in terms of the division of assets and so on,
then they could actually use the כתובה ketubah, as the basis right
for you know for determining that, how to divide the assets. And
if the wife let's say is a good earner and the husband
is not such a good earner you know they could say well
you've earned X amount of money but that's all his right because
he's provided for you you know for his salary was enough to
put food on the table, he's provided for you the מזונות, mezonos,
so you know he's entitled to all the money you've earned in
the course of your you know in the course of your ten
years of marriage. So what are you going to do about that?
So קולך Kolech basically came up with a rider on the כתובה.
ketubah. Which basically said the woman first says אי אפשי בתקנת חכמים.
ee efshi betakanat chachamim. Okay. She basically, yeah, I mean, that's in
the כתובה ketubah itself. They sort of have a separate document, but
it says it. She basically is saying I don't want my husband's
מזונות, mezonot, I'm going to keep my earnings to myself. Now, where
do you go from there? You could say that people keep separate
accounts, right? But no, but then they say after we've got to
that state that he's not obligated in מזונות mezonot and she's entitled
to her own earnings, now they're going to enter into a new
agreement where they're going to agree to share their earnings and to
share the responsibilities of מזונות. mezonot. So to make it like, you
know, what's it, what's it called, shared assets or whatever. So, you
know, so in that type of a case, that would lead to
an equal division of assets if the marriage were ever terminate, because
they're basically committing to share the responsibilities of the household and to
share, yes, the earnings. Yes, but that's the way normal stuff works,
you know, in secular law in general. They do, they don't say
who was the bigger earner, they do an equal division of assets.
So they sort of because of this, they're able to get to
that because they, because she's in the position to say I don't
want, I don't want this, אי אפשי בתקנת
חכמים.
ee efshi
betakanat chachamim.
You know what's funny? I have a, what, I have good friends
who've been married for thirty years, just a terrible marriage, whatever, and
they, they got divorced and the, his civil attorney said exactly that.
Like, she was the prime earner for those years, right, when it
comes to the divorce she needed to divide all of her savings,
right, and give him half.
Yeah, but most,
it depleted her savings.
I understand, but we live in a that's the basic law of
the land, you know? It's like what's there's a word for that,
not shared assets, what is it? Community assets? What? Community assets or
community property? Community property, yeah. Down, right. Yeah, well, that's why people
write, that's why, that's what real non-halakhic prenuptial agreements are exactly that.
That if somebody comes in with a large, you know, inheritance or
there's some type of thing and people want to protect their assets,
they write a prenuptial agreement exactly for that purpose. So that's
what, so that's the context of the original statement of כל אומר
אי אפשי בתקנת חכמים כגון זאת שומעין לו. kol omer ee efshi
betakanat chachamim kegon zot shomin lo. So it's,
I mean it's really שומעין לה. shomin la. But the original context
of that statement was a woman who says I'm going to keep
my earnings, you keep your מזונות. mezonot. So we're applying it here
too that the husband can say I'm going to, I am going
to waive my right to the אכילת פירות. achilat peirot. Now let
me say an interesting thing about the אכילת פירות. achilat perot, Every,
all, each, every one of these תנאי כתובה, tnai ktuva, there's some
type of a, of a reciprocity.
If we're going to give so-and-so this, they get, the other person
gets that in exchange. We're going to give the wife מזונות, mezonot,
that's the עיקר, ikar, the husband is going to get the מעשה
ידיים ma'aseh yadayim in exchange, the earnings. So if the husband gets
the פירות, peirot, what does the wife get in exchange? So what
the wife gets in exchange is the husband has to redeem her
if she's ever taken captive. Now that might seem a little unfair.
Here he is, he's eating פירות perot on a regular basis, right,
but if you can imagine if it were to ever happen, the
price would be a very, very high price, right? So it would
be like, you know, it would almost be like catastrophic insurance or
something like that, right? So it could be a million dollars but
then it could be you never have to pay for it, so
you know, you pay premium, think about it that way. The husband's
eating of the פירות perot are the
annual premiums, okay, in the insurance policy. Could be you'll never see
those premiums back, but the insurance policy is that you get redeemed.
Okay. So the question is, and even if it exceeds the value
of the פירות, peirot that's the whole point of paying premium. So
the question is who is seen as the primary beneficiary of that?
Is it that primarily we wanted to give the husband that right
and in exchange he has to promise this to the wife or
vice versa? So this גמרא Gemara makes it sound that if he
can say I am waiving my right of פירות, peirot, it makes
it sound like he's the primary beneficiary and he can say I
am waiving my right and therefore he's not going to be obligated
to redeem his wife. Okay. Now the funny, now תוספות, Tosafot, right,
because that's what the גמרא Gemara is trying to say, that the
husband can waive his right, that means that we're defining him as
the primary beneficiary. תוספות Tosafot actually says that this isn't true. Because
first of all, think about the following case. Let's say the wife
brings very little property into the estate. So he can just say
you know, how much am I going to get out of this?
Very little. Okay, I'm waiving my right. And now he's never going
to have to redeem his wife, right? And so תוספות Tosafot says
number one it seems to תוספות Tosafot that it's actually the reverse,
that the primary beneficiary is the wife, okay, and that therefore and
that and that's to make sure that she gets redeemed. Number two
is that he says even if the husband is like the beneficiary,
it could be that we don't want to allow him, this might
logically be an exception to the rule. We don't want to allow
him the ability to waive it because we want to ensure that
the wife is not, doesn't stay in the hands of the non-Jewish
captors, right? So it really, you know, so תוספות Tosafot really seriously
questions whether he can actually do this. He also makes another interesting
point which I want to say, which is the question of time.
timing. Okay, the idea of מעשה ידיים ומזונות Maaseh Yadayim ve-Mezonot is
like ongoing. So at any time in the marriage, the wife can
say like, I want to start keeping my—I've now just got a
nice raise, you know, and I'm now making a lot of money.
I want to now change the terms. I want to now start
keep my מעשה ידיים Maaseh Yadayim and let the guy keep the
מזונות. Mezonot. And then you can reverse that at a later stage
because
it's—what?
Once
you—it's not—once you did it, you're locked in. You can keep on—because
it's an ongoing sort of reality. Here, where you're paying a lot,
you're paying up-front for some possible future thing, you can't change the
terms in the middle. It's like, oh, let me, you know, now
that I'm eighty years old, now let me take out life insurance
based on the same premiums that I was going to pay before,
right? It doesn't work that way. So here it's like, you know,
you have to sort of make that decision at—in the beginning. It's
another interesting distinction תוספות Tosafos makes. But the more important point is
that תוספות Tosafos says for us that he doesn't think the husband
can ever really give up his right to redeem his wife. So
he doesn't exactly explain how he would explain the סוגיא, but it
must be that what תוספות Tosafos is saying is, if you want
to give up your אכילת פירות, achilat peirot, be my guest. You're
still going to have to redeem your wife. Okay, because תוספות Tosafos
says that the husband is not in a position to say, I'm
not going to do this and I'm not going to take this
and therefore
not have this responsibility.
Yeah, unless you basically want to just be, I don't know, a
nice guy. You have enough property of your own and you want
to say, you know, and therefore you don't want—you're going to be
a nice guy. But it doesn't free you from the obligation of
redeeming the wife. Did you have a question?
Yeah, the health insurance analogy is very apt, especially in countries other
than the United States, because is there an obligation for the community
at large to redeem a person? Yes. So what's the value of
the husband having to redeem?
That we don't have to put it—anyway. Right. So we don't have
to put it on
the—so what's the value that then is being given in exchange for
the פירות Peiros according to that?
Well, that we don't—you're saying—I mean, the value is that we don't
put that responsibility on the community.
It's not a value to the woman; it's a value to the
community.
Well, I think it's a value because if it's
a—it may be because maybe the funds are more readily available.
Right. And I think the question is when something is an individual
obligation. I mean, it's an interesting question, you know, but since when
does—I mean,
you know, obviously the family members are more—right, they're more likely
to redeem and so on. Right.
But in theory, the community.
I don't know. But let's say you're living in a poor town
and it's hard to raise the funds and I mean, so you
know, and if it's a personal obligation and he's been getting all
of this all this time. But I think that's an interesting question.
Like, so why do you say that the analogy to health insurance
is helpful in that regard?
Because you're saying that the פירות Peiros are in return for the
potential redemption. Right. I'm saying that the redemption should occur—it in theory
should occur anyway.
Oh, you're the Canadian one; you want socialized healthcare. I
see. Okay. Okay, that's a good question.
I'd have to look into that. But I—again, I just assume it
just seems that our communal responsibilities don't always
get done. I mean, you know, so—practically, you're right.
But in theory—right, in theory.
Yeah, if the community really was good at taking—shouldering that
responsibility. Right. Then—but the also question is if you could imagine a
wealthy man's wife was taken—and I'm not talking
about a wealthy person, it could be small amounts.
I know, but think about this. Let's say the guy's a millionaire
and they're asking therefore, you know, whatever, they're asking for a million
dollars. So now the community has to equally divide that million dollars.
Again, that's a benefit to the community.
You know, it's—sure, the wife benefits by being redeemed. But in theory,
again, she should be redeemed in any case. Who pays for it
is the question. Right.
So
you're
saying that the husband is going to set the—that the property is
going to pay for it. Right. And that's the benefit for which
he—against—I understand. All right, all
right, interesting.
You—yes, the Canadian. This is just an addition to the rabbinical perspective.
In other words, the
most—I imagine that most women did not have an income that would
obviously just reject—right.
So, I mean, it's—that's why, that's why it's primarily for her benefit.
Because in the time of חז"ל, Chazal, most women, what they would
earn would be like a few dollars by doing some sewing for
people or whatever. So—right.
So in other words, are they writing for—the majority of the population
is in—does not have
largesse.
Right. Right. So this is primarily to protect the interests of the
woman. Yes, Michal.
This seems to other—I don't know, I don't know if it's metaphors
or extensions to this פדיון שבויים pidyon shvuyim business.
What do you mean?
I don't know. It just seems such a narrow thing
that they wanted to protect against this. Yes, but that's—but it was
a reality. But that's why I'm saying... it's sort of
like they actually have health care policies which are just for what's
it called catastrophic? Right. Things that would only occur one in a
million times, but if it is, it's going to cost a fortune.
So, I think that...
But that was more common, taking captives. Right. This is in גמרא
Gemara all over the place. Yeah, and that's not as far out
then as it is now.
Right. Right.
That is correct. Like you have the משנה Mishnah. באין פודים את
השבויים יתר כדי דמיהן... ba'ein podim et hashvuyim yeter k'dei demeihen...
for parts of the world now...
exactly, there are parts of the world, yeah, businessmen go traveling they
have to be afraid, right, exactly. I think
okay. Alright, so that's the case. So that was a very fascinating
digression, and the point was that, what was the point? That it's
possible that he doesn't have a חיוב פירות kiyuv peirot and nevertheless
he doesn't have a חזקה, Chazakah. because even though he's not legally
entitled, we'll say maybe he's eating from... his wife is not מקפיד
makpid if him to eat from it anyway. Okay. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. כגון זאת. k'gon zot. So מאי כגון
זאת? mai k'gon zot? Oh, you see I already said it without
reading the next line. So מאי כגון זאת? mai k'gon zot? כי
הא דרב הונא אמר רב, ki ha d'Rav Huna amar Rav, דאמר
רב הונא אמר רב, d'amar Rav Huna amar Rav, יכולה אשה שתאמר
לבעלה איני ניזונת ואיני עושה. yacholah ishah shetomer l'ba'alah eini nizonet v'eini
osah. Okay, the woman can say to her husband, 'I will not
be fed by you and I am not going to work for
you. I am not going to... you are not going to benefit
from my labor.' Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara switches gears. Yes.
Didn't you say Libman that's like literally... so you're saying not as
written in the כתובה, ketubah right? Correct. So how are we going
to know? So he's saying this is mine, and then she's saying
this is...
She has whatever evidence anybody has to the fact that land is
there.
Right, but like 20 years later, the witnesses are no longer around,
so what do we do?
Oh, so that's a question that תוספות Tosafot says that, you know,
why if let's say you're eating a... you're eating
all the fruit of my land because of a משכנתא דסורא, mashkanta
d'Sura, people might think it's yours. And what I would have to
do is every three years make a מחאה machah and say everybody
should be aware that Michael is there just because of a משכנתא,
mashko, it's not his land. But here the wife does not have
to do that because everybody knows that the husband eats the fruits
of the wife's property. So therefore, once she can bring evidence that
it used to be her property, even if he's been eating from
it for 20 years, everybody knows that's the nature of the marriage.
But what evidence
can she have as evidence?
She doesn't need that evidence, she needs the...
right...
if she's afraid that because he's eating it so long people are
going to forget that it used to be her property, then she
better make a מחאה machah or do something.
Yeah, I just want to make sure I'm not mistaken. So if
he...
if he gives up his right to the מזון... mazon... to מעשה
ידיה... ma'aseh yadeiha... yeah, and she's captured, he doesn't have to redeem...
No, תוספות Tosafot says that he could give up his right to
מעשה ידיה ma'aseh yadeiha if he wants, but
he still has to redeem her because you do not have the
right to not redeem your wife. Right. That's what תוספות Tosafot says.
Now community, that's what Dov is saying. תוספות Tosafot says he still
has that right. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara... says like this.
Okay, the other day. גמרא Gemara says, now, הראיה יש. harayah yesh.
Now, okay, so the husband doesn't have a חזקה, Chazakah but he
would have a ראיה rayah if he produced her שטר that said,
you know, that his wife sold him this plot of land that
used to be her and it had witnesses on it, presumably that
would work. It's just a חזקה Chazakah that doesn't work. But one
minute, maybe it doesn't work. So הראיה, harayah, תימא נחת רוח עשיתי
לבעלי. teima nachat ruach asiti l'ba'ali. The woman can say, 'Yeah, I
went along with it and I said I was selling him the
land and I got witnesses to sign it, but it was because...
yeah, I wasn't really serious. I only did it so he wouldn't
be angry at me. So he wouldn't, you know, sort of like
the coercion before, except like a different type of coercion, you know?
Nothing is explicitly being said, but I did it because, you know,
he's my husband, I didn't want to get him angry, but I
didn't really... I didn't really want to sell it.' So the גמרא...
Gemara so now how do we know that that's a legitimate claim
against witnesses that say you sold it? מי לא תנן, mi lo
tnan, because we have a משנה. לקח מן האיש וחזר ולקח מן
האשה מקחו בטל. lakach min ha'ish v'chazar v'lakach min ha'ishah mekachu batel.
Let's say I went ahead and I bought from the husband... the
husband is now eating the נכסי מלוג, nichsei milug, he's eating the
fruit of the נכסי מלוג. nichsei milog, I go ahead from the
husband and I buy from him his right of אכילת פירות, Peiros
and then I go to the wife and I buy from her
the title. And now I can... I should own it fully. I
bought his נכסי... his פירות and her title, and now I should
own it fully. It says מקחו בטל, mekachu batel, it's invalid. Why?
Why is it invalid? אמר, אמר נחת רוח עשיתי לבעלי. amar, amar
nachat ruach asiti l'ba'ali. Because she can say, 'it was clear my
husband wanted to sell you the plot of the land, he was
willing to sell you the פירות, so I like went along and
I sold you my title, but I wasn't serious about that.' So
הכא נמי, hacha nami, let her say the same... let her say
the same thing here. So the גמרא says no. אימר לה, immar
lah, אמר רבה בר רב הונא, amar Rabbah bar Rav Huna, לא
נצרכה אלא באותן גמל שדות. lo nitzrecha ela b'otan gimel sadot. That
הלכה, halacha, that it's invalid when I bought from the husband and
the wife, we're not talking when I bought from the נכסי מלוג.
nichsei milog That is not what I bought from the husband and
the wife. If I bought the נכסי מלוג, nichsei milog it's valid.
What are we talking about? A much weaker type of a purchase.
What did I buy? אותן גמל שדות. otan gimel sadot. The three
גמל שדות gimel sadot fields that the wife has a lien on
in the כתובה. ketubah. Now, actually in the כתובה ketubah. if you
remember, wife has a lien... on everything, right? We discussed that once
before, on the קרקע, karka, it even says on the מטלטלין, mataltelin,
on the stuff he's going to buy in the future. But that
being said, it could be that the כתובה ketubah? would designate certain
properties that she has a primary lien on, that she should feel
confident about those properties. What are those properties? Three of them.
אחת שכתב לה בכתובתה, Achas shekasav lah bkesuvasah, one explicitly mentioned in
the כתובה. It says you have a lien on everything and you
can including this field or whatever and this field is mentioned explicitly.
אחת שייחד לה בכתובתה, Achas sheyiched lah bkesuvasah, one that he designates.
It's not written, but he says, "this field can be for you
to collect." He says it maybe verbally.
Okay. ואחת שהכניסה לו שום משלה. Vachas shehichnisah lo shum mishelah. And
the other one that she brought in that was evaluated. What does
this mean? So the רשב"ם Rashbam says what it means—there's different reads
of these, but the רשב"ם Rashbam says it means this.
She brought in a particular field, I mean she didn't physically bring
it in, that was the, remember, נכסי צאן ברזל. That was the
נדוניא. So I basically totally took title of it. It was worth
$10,000. Now, if I divorce her or I die before her, she
can take $10,000 out of the estate. But most likely the first
thing she would want to take that $10,000 out of is this
field, okay? So the actual physical field that she brought in as
the נדוניא. Now could be that it wouldn't be enough, the value
could have gone down, it could be she'll only get half the
field, the value went up. But nevertheless, and she doesn't have to
take the $10,000 out of this field, she could take it out
of something else. But because this was the field she brought in,
that will be the one that she actually has a primary interest
in taking when it's the time to collect her כתובה. Okay, so
therefore we're talking about fields that she basically, it's not her נכסי
מלוג, nichsei milog. it's not ones she doesn't have title to, she
just has a lien on those fields. So here's what happened. I
went to the husband and I—we're not talking about נכסי מלוג—I nichsei
milog, went to the husband and I just wanted to buy one
of his fields. Okay, but it happened to be a field that
the wife had a special lien. She really has a lien on
all the property, but these are the ones that she has particularly
in mind that she will collect from. So I bought that from
the husband and then I went to the wife and I basically
wanted to pay her some money to waive her lien. That's what
I'm doing, I'm not buying the field from the wife. I wanted
to pay her some money to waive her lien. So I paid
her money to waive her lien, and there it says that in
that case, it says she can say "I didn't really give up
my lien. I was only doing it because
נחת רוח עשיתי לבעלי." nachas ruach asisi lbaali. My husband already sold
you the entire field, I wanted to make it now, and part
of the reason also that's נחת רוח nachas ruach is because to
hold onto the lien means what? If she's holding onto the lien,
what's she anticipating?
That he's
going to die or that he's going to divorce her, right? So
therefore, "you already bought the field from my husband, we're just talking
about a lien, my husband would really have not looked good if
I would have wanted to hold onto that lien. So I went
along, but I didn't really mean it." That's where we say that
that's not a legitimate purchase from the wife. The wife still has
the lien. But to actually buy the נכסי מלוג nichsei milog, from
the wife, that would actually be a good sale. Okay.
The first of the three fields,
we don't do this anymore. It's literally written in, north-eastern corner.
Exactly, exactly, exactly.
And even regarding the איני ניזונת eini nizonet and all that.
Right, right, let's just finish this point. So the גמרא says, למעוטי
מאי? Lmautei mai? So what these three fields, what are they excluding?
אילימא למעוטי שאר נכסים? Ileima lmautei shar nechasim? Let's say it was
about that about another piece of property. Somebody bought some סתם stam
property, not one of these three, and then wanted to get the
wife to waive her liens.
Would we—and then she did—would we still say because she could still
say "I was just doing this to make my husband happy"? So
כל שכן דהויא לה איבה. Kol shekein dhava lei eivah. So certainly
she can say by other
fields that she was doing it to prevent the husband from being
angry at her. דאמר לה עיניך נתת בגירושין ובמיתה. Damar lah einayich
nasat bgeirushin uvmisa. Because he would say, "I don't understand, why are
you holding onto liens of this property that's not even the primary
property of your כתובה? You're so worried that I'm going to die
or I'm going to divorce you that you want to make sure
not only you have liens on the property that—the special property, but
even on this second-class property?" So that, of course, she would say
"I'm just doing it not to get him upset. That's why I
agreed to sell
it." אלא למעוטי נכסי מלוג. Ela lmautei nichsei milog. It must be
to exclude the case of נכסי מלוג. Nikhsei Milug, That if she
sells נכסי מלוג, it really is a good sale. This idea—and that's
also more of a relief because anytime you have testimony that a
woman, somebody sold something and said "Yeah, I didn't really mean it,"
right, it a little bit undermines the whole system, right? So now
we're saying that it only works when she's saying she didn't waive
a lien. But if she actually sold her נכסי מלוג, that would
be a good sale and she can't say "I was only doing
it to make my husband happy." And therefore if he actually brings
a שטר... That he sold it to him, it actually is a
good sale. Okay, so she doesn't have a חזקה, Chazakah. he doesn't
have a חזקה Chazakah, on the נכסי מלוג, but if he has
a ראיה, Rayah, if he has a שטר, it would be good.
Mike? Yeah, but what about the איני ניזונת ואיני מעשה, Einni Nizonet
v'Eini Mo'ese, the whole thing about איני ניזונת ואיני מעשה? Einni Nizonet
v'Eini Mo'ese?
That's just to say that why when he doesn't have a חזקה.
He doesn't have a חזקה certainly if he has his normal פירות
rights, but even if he's waived his פירות rights, he doesn't have
a חזקה because she could let him eat the fruit without saying
anything, it is her husband. Okay, so that's the cases in when
he doesn't have a חזקה. So איני ניזונת Einni Nizonet is just
like a חידוש, Chiddush, even if he's waived his פירות rights, he
still doesn't have a חזקה, but a ראיה Rayah he would have.
Yes.
Is this wife's denial as to the husband denies he's divorced her?
Yes, presumably. Presumably. Okay, great. Okay, so פורים שמח, Purim Sameach, we
will continue tomorrow.
You
know I was thinking more about this, the...